水善
Water.
土强
Earth.
火烈
Fire.
气和
Air.
很久以前,这四大国和谐共处
Long ago, the four nations lived together in harmony.
然而,火国发起的战争结束了和平
Then everything changed when the Fire Nation attacked.
只有同时掌握四种元素的降世神通
Only the Avatar, master of all four elements,
才能结束战争
could stop them.
然而在大家最需要他的时候,他却消失了
But when the world needed him most, he vanished.
100年后,我和哥哥发现了新的降世神通
100 years passed, and my brother and I discovered the new Avatar,
他是个御气师,名叫安昂
an airbender named Aang.
尽管他的御气术着实厉害
And although his airbending skills are great,
但在拯救苍生之前,他要学的还有很多
he has a lot to learn before he's ready to save anyone.
呃!
Unh!
但是我坚信安昂能拯救这个世界
But I believe Aang can save the world.
降世神通 最后的气宗
第一卷 水 第十二回 风暴
我们需要你,安昂
We need you, Aang.
我也需要你们
I need you, too.
小心啊,伙计们
Be careful, guys!
大家都去哪了?
Guys?
嘉措大师?
Gyatso?
你为什么不辞而别?
Why did you disappear?
我不是故意的
I didn't mean to.
我们需要你,安昂
We need you, Aang.
啊!
Aaaaah!!!
我们需要你,安昂, 我们需要你
We need you, Aang. We need you.
怎么了?
Huh! What's going on?
我们又被抓了吗?
Did we get captured again?
没事,我做了一个噩梦而已
It's nothing. I just had a bad dream.
继续睡吧
Go back to sleep.
天哪,我都被你弄醒两次了
You don't have to tell me twice.
你还好吧,安昂?
Are you all right, Aang?
我还好
I'm okay.
你最近好像老做噩梦
You seem to be having a lot of nightmares lately.
想不想跟我谈谈?
You want to tell me about it?
没事的,我想我只是需要多休息休息
Ithinkijust need some rest.
你们想不想知道我梦到了什么?
You guys want to hear about my dream?
没事,一般人我还不告诉他呢
That's okay. I didn't want to talk about it anyway.
伙计们快看,天气多好啊
Look at those clear skies, buddy.
这种天气飞行再好不过啦
Should be some smooth flying.
咱们最好赶快飞去市场
Well, we'd better smoothly fly ourselves to a market,
因为我们的食物都已经吃光了
because we're out of food.
伙计们等等,这正如我的梦一样
Guys, wait. This was in my dream.
我们今天不能去市场
We shouldn't go to the market.
你都梦见什么了?
What happened in your dream?
食物会吃人啊!
Food eats people!
还有,模模开口说人话了
Also, Momo could talk.
你可说了一堆不友好的话哦
You said some very unkind things.
有一场暴风雨即将来临
There is a storm coming.
而且,来势不小啊
A big one.
你糊涂了吧,皇叔
You're out of your mind, uncle.
今天天气这么好
The weather is perfect.
万里无云
There's not a cloud in sight.
这场风暴从北方逼近
A storm is approaching from the north.
我建议更改航线,向西南行驶
I suggest we alter our course and head southwest.
我们都知道降世神通在向北行
We know the Avatar is traveling northward,
所以我们也必须如此
so we will do the same.
祖寇殿下,你要考虑一下船员的安危
Prince Zuko, consider the safety of the crew.
船员的安危无关紧要!
The safety of the crew doesn't matter.
找到降世神通远比
Finding the Avatar is far more important
任何人的安危都来得重要
than any individual's safety.
请别误会,他只是一时头脑发热
He doesn't mean that. He's just all worked up.
哎呀,你听我说的准没错,这瓜简直完美
It's good. It's perfect, I'm telling you.
我总觉得里面听起来稀里光趟的
I don't know if I like the sound of that swishing.
稀里光趟的才好呢
Swishing means it's ripe.
说明瓜熟了,明白不?
It's the ripe juices swishing around, huh?
没错的,卡塔拉
I think it's true, Katara.
稀里光趟的就熟了
Swishing means it's ripe.
我刚发现我们钱不够
I just realized we're out of money, anyway.
喔...
Aww...
吃的没了,现在钱又花光了
Out of food and out of money.
现在该怎么办啊?
Now what are we supposed to do?
你们可以去打个工,聪明人
You could get a job, smart guy.
我们不该出海!
We shouldn't go out there.
求你了,鱼哪天不能打啊
Please! The fish can wait.
今天将有大风暴
There's going to be a terrible storm.
别说胡话!这么好的天
Aw, you're crazy. It's a nice day.
没云、没风、没闪电的
No clouds, no wind, no nothing,
所以别跟我唠叨了
so quit your nagging, woman.
也许咱们该找个地方避一避
Maybe we should find some shelter.
开什么玩笑,避什么啊?
Are you kidding? Shelter from what?
我的关节痛告诉我有一场暴风雨即将来临
My joints say there's going to be a storm,
还是很大的一场
a bad one.
别拿你的关节跟我的脑子比
Well, it's your joints against my brain.
那叫你的脑子找别人拖网吧
Then I hope your brain can find someone else to haul that fish,
反正我是不会去的!
‘cause I ain't coming!
那我就另找个新的渔夫!
Then I'll find a new fish hauler,
还付他双倍的工钱!
and pay him double what you get.
这下你高兴了吧
How do you like that?
我要去!
I'll go.
你被雇了
You're hired.
怎么啦?你不是说要找份工作吗
What? You said get a job.
他还付双倍工钱呢
And he's paying double.
双倍工钱?你听谁胡诌的?
Double? Who told you that nonsense?
呃!看来真让你的皇叔说着了
Oh. Looks like your uncle was right about the storm after all.
侥幸猜中而已
Lucky guess.
上尉,你最好学习一下如何尊敬别人
Lieutenant, you'd better learn some respect,
不然我只能亲自教你了
or I will teach it to you.
说到尊敬,你懂什么叫尊敬吗?
What do you know about respect?
瞧瞧你对周围人说话的态度
The way you talk to everyone around here,
不论是为你辛苦工作的船员,还是你应当尊敬的皇叔
from your hard-working crew to your esteemed uncle,
你根本就不懂得什么叫尊敬
shows you know nothing about respect.
你只在乎你自己的感受
You don't care about anyone but yourself.
再说,我怎么能期望从一个被宠坏的王子那里得到尊敬呢
Then again, what should I expect from a spoiled prince?
你们都冷静点
Easy now.
够了!
Enough!
可能是出海太久了,大家都累了
We're all a bit tired from being at sea so long.
我相信大家一块吃碗面条
I'm sure after a bowl of noodles,
能让每个人的心情都好一点
everyone will feel much better.
我不需要你来维护我的船的秩序
I don't need your help keeping order on my ship.
索卡,你还是别出海了
Sokka, maybe this isn't such a good idea.
瞧,这都变天了
Look at the sky.
我说过了这活我干定了
I said I was gonna do this job.
我可不会因为什么坏天气就放弃的
I can't back out just because of some bad weather.
这个有纹身的小子还有点脑子
The boy with the tattoos has some sense.
你应该听他的
You should listen to him.
带纹身的小子?
Boy with tattoos?
这不是气和族的纹身吗?
Airbender tattoos.
活见鬼了
Well, I'll be a hog monkey's uncle.
你是降世神通,对吧?
You're the Avatar, ain't you?
如假包换
That's right.
别摆出那副笑脸!
Well, don't be so smiley about it.
神通消失了近百年了
The Avatar disappeared for a hundred years!
你背弃了这个世界!
You turned your back on the world.
别冲他嚷
Don't yell at him!
安昂从没有背弃任何人
Aang would never turn his back on anyone.
哦,他没有吗?
Oh, he wouldn't, huh?
那持续了百年的战争和痛苦
Then I guess I must have imagined
都是我想像出来的了
the last hundred years of war and suffering.
安昂是我见过的最勇敢的人
Aang is the bravest person I know.
自从我认识他以来
He has done nothing but help people,
他一直都在帮助他人,拯救生命
and save lives since I met him.
当初消失并不是他的错,我说得没错吧,安昂
It's not his fault he disappeared, right, Aang?
安昂,怎么了?
Aang, what's wrong?
这就对了,继续飞!
That's right! Keep flying!
你这个老头真可恶
You're a horrible old man!
阿柏,驾,驾
Appa, yip yip!
啊!
Uhh!
嘿,他们居然没说一声就走了
Hey! They left without saying good-bye.
你的朋友怎么这么没礼貌
Your friends ain't too polite, are they?
那可不是嘛,你知道曾经吧...
I know. This one time, I was-Yeah,
行了,别唠叨了,把这些拿舱里去
yeah, yeah. Get below deck.
我很抱歉我跑掉了
I'm sorry for running away.
没关系,那个打渔的太过分了
It's okay. That fisherman was way out of line.
其实他没说错
Actually, he wasn't.
这话怎么说?
What do you mean?
我现在不想谈这个
I don't want to talk about it.
这跟你这几天做的噩梦有关,对吗
It has to do with your dream, doesn't it?
跟我说说吧
Talk to me.
好吧,说来话长啊
Well, it's kind of a long story.
我去生火
I'm gonna try to get a little fire going.
长老们告诉我我就是降世神通那天,我终生难忘
I'll never forget the day the monks told me I was the Avatar.
当时,我和其他的小孩在南墙外玩耍
I was playing with some other kids just outside the south wall.
我正在教他们如何玩「气轮球」
I was trying to teach them how to do the air scooter.
首先你得先把气凝成球状,然后快速骑上
First you form a ball. Then you've got to get on quick.
哈哈哈!
Ha ha ha!
耶!哈哈哈!
Yeah! Ha ha ha!
喔吼!耶!
Whoo-hoo! Yeah!
好的,让我试试
Okay, here goes.
快,骑上
Quick. Get on.
哇 哇
Whoa. Whoa...
哦!
Uhh!
这个气轮球就像个陀螺一样,你得学会在上面保持平衡
You kind of have to balance on it like it's a top.
天哪,真是太难了
Man, that's hard.
安昂,你是在哪学会这招的?
Where did you learn that trick, Aang?
我自创的
I made it up.
哇!
Wow!
安昂,跟我们来
Aang, come with us.
我们有话要跟你说
We need to speak with you.
你们怎么知道会是我?
How do you know it's me?
我们早就知道你是降世神通了
We have known you were the Avatar for some time.
你还记得这些东西吗?
Do you remember these?
这些是我小时候最喜爱的玩具
Those were some of my favorite toys when I was little.
安昂,你从上千个玩具中单单选中了这几样
You chose them from among thousands of toys, Aang.
你挑的这几样玩具是四位神通的遗物
The toys you picked were the four Avatar relics.
这些东西属于神通前世
These items belonged to Avatars past.
也就是你的前世
Your own past lives.
我选它们,只是因为它们看上去很好玩
I just chose them because they seemed fun.
你选它们是因为你熟悉它们
You chose them because they were familiar.
一般来说我们会在你16岁后告诉你的身份
Normally, we would have told you of your identity when you turned 16.
然而天有不测风云
But there are troubling signs.
一场风暴即将来临
Storm clouds are gathering.
恐怕战争已经逼近这儿了,年轻的神通
I fear that war may be upon us, young Avatar.
我们需要你,安昂
We need you, Aang.
我听够他的命令了
I'm sick of taking his orders,
我也不想再追什么神通了
and I'm tired of chasing his Avatar.
祖寇以为他自己是谁啊?
I mean, who does Zuko think he is?
你们真的想知道吗?
Do you really want to know?
艾洛将军,我们只是...
General lroh, we were just--
没关系
It's okay.
我能加入你们吗?
May I join you?
当然可以,长官
Of course, sir.
请试着去理解他吧
Try to understand,
我的侄子是个复杂的年轻人
my nephew is a complicated young man.
他经历的太多了
He has been through much.
让我进去
Let me in!
祖寇殿下,怎么了?
Prince Zuko, what's wrong?
我想进军情室
I want to go into the war chamber,
但是警卫不让我进去
but the guard won't let me pass.
相信我,里面没什么可看的
You're not missing anything. Trust me.
这些会议无聊透顶
These meetings are dreadfully boring.
如果终有一天我将统治这个国家
If I'm going to rule this nation one day,
你不觉得我应该从现在开始尽可能地多学一些东西吗?
don't you think I need to start learning as much as I can?
很好,但你得保证绝不开口
Very well, but you must promise not to speak.
你也知道这些老家伙们都有些敏感
These old folks are a bit sensitive, you know?
多谢您皇叔
Thank you, uncle.
土强国的抵抗力量都集中在这里
The Earth Kingdom defenses are concentrated here,
那是一支由最强的御土师
a dangerous battalion of their strongest earth benders,
和最骁勇的战士们组成的危险队伍
and fiercest warriors.
所以我建议将第41师派往这里
So, I am recommending the 41st division.
但是41师全都是由新兵组成的
But the 41st is entirely new recruits.
他们怎么可能击败这么强大的土强国军团
How do you expect them to defeat a powerful Earth Kingdom battalion?
他们是不行
I don't.
他们不过是用来掩人耳目的
They'll be used as a distraction
我们将从敌军的后防进攻
while we mount an attack from the rear.
做诱饵,当然得用新鲜的肉了
What better to use as bait than fresh meat?
你不能就这样牺牲掉整个师
You can't sacrifice an entire division like that!
这些战士热爱并守护着我们的国家
Those soldiers love and defend our nation.
你怎么能背叛他们?
How can you betray them?
祖寇说得没错,不是吗
Zuko was right, you see?
但在这里他没有资格发言
But it was not his place to speak out.
于是接踵而来的是无法想像的恶果
And there were dire consequences.
所以,发现自己是神通你感到很沮丧?
So you were upset that you were the Avatar?
你应该感到激动才对啊?
Why wouldn't you be excited about it?
我也不知道对此应该有什么感觉
Well, I didn't know how to feel about it.
我只知道,在我得知这个消息之后
All I knew was that after I found out,
一切都改变了
everything began changing.
嘿,不错啊
Hey, not bad.
你们都练过了是吧
You guys have been practicing.
我们不光练习了
Not only that,
还想出了一个用气轮球玩的游戏呢
we made up a game you can play with the air scooters.
太棒了!
Great!
怎么了?
What's going on?
现在你是降世神通了
Now that you're the Avatar,
把你分到哪一组
iVs kind of an unfair advantage
对其他组来说都是不公平的
for whichever team you're on.
但是,我还是我啊
But I'm still the same.
我并没有变
Nothing has changed.
怎么,我不能玩了?
So, what? I can't play?
只有这样对大家才公平啊
That's the only fair way.
哦,好吧
Oh, okay...
抱歉了,安昂
Sorry, Aang.
好,哪队愿意让「金九」加入?
Okay, now, who wants to have Jinju on their team?
你这步下得很有意思啊,小神通
Very interesting move, young one.
为什么这么说?
What do you mean?
嘿!哈哈哈!
Hey! Ha ha ha!
哈哈哈!
Ha ha ha!
你竟然在这儿和他玩上了?
You're playing games with him?
神通现在需要加紧修炼
The Avatar should be training.
安昂今天已经练得够多的了
Aang has already trained enough for today.
时间紧迫,跟我来
Time is short. Come with me.
我得考考你对一些上层招式的理解
I must test you on some high-level techniques.
不行,只要我是他的监护人一天
No. As long as I am his guardian,
我就有权决定他何时修炼
I will decide when he trains
以及何时在牌手棋盘上显丑
And when he gets his butt kicked at Pai Sho.
哼!
Hmmph!
由于祖寇在那次会议上的失态
After Zuko's outburst in the meeting,
火烈王震怒
the Fire Lord became very angry with him.
他说祖克殿下对将军的挑战
He said that Prince Zuko's challenge of the general
完全是一种无礼的行为
was an act of complete disrespect.
而对于这种行为只有一种了结的方法
And there was only one way to resolve this.
火神祭——火功对决
Agni Kai. A fire duel.
Agni Kai, Agni是一个火神,Kai在日语中有集会的意思
没错
That's right.
祖寇没把他得罪的老将军放在眼里
Zuko looked upon the old general he had insulted,
毫无畏惧地应战了
and declared that he was not afraid.
但是祖克误解了
But Zuko misunderstood.
当他面对他的对手时
When he turned to face his opponent,
他诧异地发现对手并不是那个将军
he was surprised to see it was not the general.
祖克出言顶撞了将军的计划
Zuko had spoken out against the general's plan,
但他是在火烈国君的议战厅里讲出这些话的
but by doing so in the Fire Lord's war room,
他无视的是火烈国之王
it was the Fire Lord whom he had disrespected.
所以祖克不得不跟他的生身父亲进行较量
Zuko would have to duel his own father.
当我刚刚感觉好点的时候
Then, just when I was starting to feel better,
更糟的事发生了
something worse happened.
安昂需要自由和快乐
Aang needs to have freedom and fun.
他理应像正常的孩子一样成长
He needs to grow up as a normal boy.
哼!不管你怎样保护他,他终究要面对自己的命运
Hmm. You cannot keep protecting him from his destiny.
嘉措,我知道你是好心
Gyatso, I know you mean well,
但是你对这孩子的关爱蒙蔽了你的判断力
but you are letting your affection for the boy cloud your judgment.
我只是想一心为他好
All I want is what is best for him.
可是我们需要为天下人着想
But what we need is what's best for the world.
你和安昂必须分开
You and Aang must be separated.
神通将会被送去东气和寺
The Avatar will be sent away to the Eastern Air Temple
完成他的修炼
to complete his training.
那可真糟糕啊,安昂
That's awful, Aang.
我不知该说些什么
I don't know what to say.
他们怎么能这样对我
How could they do that to me?
他们竟然要把我所了解的东西
They wanted to take away everything I knew,
还有我所爱的人都从我身边带走!
and everyone I loved!
啊!安昂,小心火炭!
Whoa! Hot cinders.
对不起,我有点失态了
I'm sorry I got so mad.
长老们就这样把你送走是不对的
You have a right to be angry
你有理由生气
after the monks sent you away like that.
其实,事情还没有发展到那步
Well, that's not exactly what happened.
当时我既害怕又困惑
I was afraid and confused.
我不知道该怎么做
I didn't know what to do.
安昂?
Aang?
我不会让他们把你从我身边带走的
I'm not going to let them take you away from me.
安昂?
Aang?
啊...
Aah...
从那以后,我再也没有见过嘉措大师
I never saw Gyatso again.
啊!
Aaaah!
之后我只记得你们在冰川中发现了我
Next thing I knew, I was waking up in your arms
我在你的臂弯中醒来
after you found me in the iceberg.
你出走了
You ran away.
我出走后火宗的人袭击了我们寺
And then the Fire Nation attacked our temple.
我的同胞们需要我,但我却不在那儿
My people needed me, and I wasn't there to help.
你不知道会...
You don't know what would have--
世界需要我的时候,我也没能挺身而出
The world needed me, and I wasn't there to help.
-安昂... -那个渔夫说得对
-Aang... -The fisherman was right.
我背弃了这个世界
I did turn my back on the world.
你对自己太苛求了
You're being too hard on yourself.
我想你当初的出走
Even if you did run away,
这也许是天意吧
I think it was meant to be.
如果你当初留下来
If you had stayed, you would have been killed
可能像其他的气宗人一样被杀了
along with all the other airbenders.
你不明白
You don't know that.
我知道这是天意
I know it's meant to be this way.
天下人现在需要你
The world needs you now.
你给人们带来了希望
You give people hope.
当祖寇殿下看到他的对手
When Prince Zuko saw that it was his father
竟然是他的父王时
who had come to duel him,
他向他乞求宽恕
he begged for mercy.
父王,求您了
Please, father,
我只是心系火烈国安危
I only had the Fire Nation's best interests at heart.
我很抱歉我出言不逊
I'm sorry I spoke out of turn.
你得为你的荣誉而战
You will fight for your honor.
我无意冒犯您
I meant you no disrespect.
我是您最忠心的王儿啊
I am your loyal son.
站起来较量吧,祖寇王儿
Rise and fight, Prince Zuko.
我不会与您较量的
I won't fight you.
你一定要学会如何尊敬人
You will learn respect,
痛苦将会是你最好的老师
and suffering will be your teacher.
我把脸转开了
I looked away.
啊!!!
Aaaaaaah!
我一直以为祖寇殿下是在训练中意外弄伤的
I always thought that Prince Zuko was in a training accident.
并没有什么意外
It was no accident.
决斗之后
After the duel,
国王陛下下令由于祖寇拒绝比武
the Fire Lord said that by refusing to fight,
他表现出的是令人羞愧的软弱
Zuko had shown shameful weakness.
作为惩罚他将被驱逐
As punishment, he was banished,
并派他去追捕降世神通
and sent to capture the Avatar.
只有抓住神通,那时他才可以荣归故里
Only then could he return with his honor.
所以他才如此专注
So that's why he's so obsessed.
抓住神通是他重返正常生活的
Capturing the Avatar is the only chance he has
唯一途径
of things returning to normal.
然而他的人生再也不会恢复正常了
Things will never return to normal,
不过重要的是
but the important thing is,
神通的出现给祖寇带来了希望
the Avatar gives Zuko hope.
救命啊,救命啊!
Help! Oh, please, help!
没事了,你现在安全了
It's okay. You're safe.
但我丈夫还很危险
But my husband isn't.
您此言怎讲?索卡还没回来吗?
What do you mean? Where's Sokka?
他们现在都还没回来
They haven't returned.
他们早就应该回来了
They should have been back by now.
这暴风雨就快变成台风了
And this storm is becoming a typhoon.
他们一定被困在海上了
They're caught out at sea!
我去找他们
I'm going to find them.
我也跟你一起去
I'm going with you.
我就留在这儿了
I'm staying here.
我保证,我们会很快回来的
We'll be back soon. I promise.
哪儿受损了?
Where were we hit?
我也不知道
I don't know.
看呐!
Look!
舵手
The helmsman!
啊!
Aah!
他们在哪啊?
Where are they?
加油啊,阿柏
Come on, Appa!
看呐,船在那儿呢
The boat! There!
降世神通!
The Avatar!
殿下,请您下令吧
What do you want to do, sir?
随他去吧
Let him go.
咱们得保住这艘船
We need to get this ship to safety.
那就向风暴之眼前进吧
Then we must head directly into the eye of the storm.
我还年轻,我不想死啊
I'm too young to die!
我不年轻了,但我也不想死啊!
I'm not, but I still don't want to!
抓住绳子
Hang on to the rope!
哇!哇!
Whoa! Whoa!
皇叔,我很抱歉
Uncle, I am sorry.
没关系
Your apology is accepted.
太好了,你还活着
Oh! You're alive!
你欠这个男孩子一个道歉
You owe this boy an apology.
他用不着道歉
He doesn't have to apologize.
不如,我白给他条鱼
What if, instead of an apology,
就当是我道歉了吧
I give him a free fish, and we call it even?
实际上,我不吃肉
Actually, I don't eat meat.
鱼肉可不算肉
Fish ain't meat.
说真的,你还没付我工钱呢
Seriously, you're still gonna pay me, right?
啊!
Aah!
卡塔拉,我想你之前说得对
Katara, I think you were right before.
我不再沉溺于过去了
I'm done dwelling on the past.
真的吗?
Really?
如果我之前没有出走的话
I can't make guesses about how things would have turned out
我完全无法想象事情该如何发展
If I hadn't run away.
既然我回来了,我就应该担起责任
I'm here now, and I'm going to make the most of it.
我想你再也不会做那些噩梦了
I don't think you're gonna have those nightmares anymore.
如果没有你在这里的话
If you weren't here now...
我想我可能就死在风暴里了
Well, I guess, I wouldn't be either.
神通,多谢你的救命之恩
Thank you for saving my life, Avatar.
你们听到了吗?
Do you hear that?
雨停下来了
It stopped raining.
阿柏!
Uh! Appa!
-=未完待续=-